<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rabii Elbeji</title>
    <description>Personal website</description>
    <link>https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 18:02:45 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 18:02:45 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduction to NDK for Android mobile apps</title>
        <description>&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/ndk-intro.png&quot; alt=&quot;Introduction to NDK for mobile apps&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you try to build a high-performance and optimized game or across platform application or maybe an application with advanced and complicated AI tasks in production, you most probably choose as programming language a low level one such as &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;C++&lt;/code&gt; . But if the platform is a mobile device, such as Android, is it still the same case of using a native language?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short answer: &lt;strong&gt;Yes!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Android apps can be categorized into two types:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Dalvik applications&lt;/code&gt; that include &lt;code&gt;Java&lt;/code&gt; code and use the Android official SDK API &lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; and necessary resource files, such as xml and png, compiled into an APK file.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Android NDK applications&lt;/code&gt; that include &lt;code&gt;Java&lt;/code&gt; code and resource files as well as &lt;code&gt;C/C++&lt;/code&gt; source code and sometimes assembly code. All native code is compiled into a dynamic linked library (&lt;code&gt;.so&lt;/code&gt; file) and then called by Java in the main program using a JNI mechanism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-the-ndk-and-when-should-you-use-it&quot;&gt;What is the NDK and when should you use it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Android Native Development Kit (&lt;code&gt;NDK&lt;/code&gt;) is a companion tool to the Android SDK. The NDK is a powerful tool for developing Android applications because it allow you to build  performance-critical portions of your applications in native code. When using Java code, the Java-based source code needs to be interpreted into machine language using a virtual machine. In contrast, the native code is compiled and optimized into binary directly before execution. With proper use of native code, you can build high performance code in your application, such as hardware video encoding and decoding, graphics processing, and arithmetical operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the NDK Reuses legacy native code. C/C++ codes can be compiled into a dynamic library that can be called by Java code with a &lt;code&gt;JNI&lt;/code&gt; mechanism. JNI is an abbreviation for Java Native Interface. It allows C++ and Java parts to talk to each other in the simplest terms. For example, if you want to call a function from C++ in Java, you should write a JNI interface for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you write native code, your applications are still packaged into an .apk file and they still run inside of a virtual machine on the device. The fundamental Android application model does not change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/ndk-use-cases.png&quot; alt=&quot;Android NDK use cases&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abi-application-binary-interface&quot;&gt;ABI: Application Binary Interface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, Android is distributed for a variety of devices. Each device might have a different CPU architecture. When you develop an Android application that contains C++ code, you should care about the platforms on which your application will run. The C++ code should be compiled as a library for each platform you target. You can compile the library for all the supported platforms, or you can choose to compile it for only one platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can list any subset of the ABIs the NDK supports, as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-gradle&quot;&gt;android {
    defaultConfig {
        ndk {
            // Tells Gradle to build outputs for the following ABIs and package
            // them into your APK.
             abiFilters 'x86', 'x86_64', 'armeabi-v7a', 'arm64-v8a'
        }
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When this flag is not configured, Gradle builds and packages all available ABIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/abi-cpus.png&quot; alt=&quot;ARM and Intel Mobile CPUs architectures&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/supported-abi.png&quot; alt=&quot;ABIs and supported instruction sets&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce the size of your APK, consider configuring multiple APKs based on ABI—instead of creating one large APK with all versions of your native libraries, Gradle creates a separate APK for each ABI you want to support and only packages the files each ABI needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello World project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Install the NDK, CMake, and LLDB&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under &lt;code&gt;Configure&lt;/code&gt; select &lt;code&gt;SDK Manager&lt;/code&gt; then check the &lt;strong&gt;LLDB&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;NDK&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;CMake&lt;/strong&gt; checkboxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/helloworld/step00.png&quot; alt=&quot;Select SDK Manager&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/helloworld/step0.png&quot; alt=&quot;Install the NDK, CMake, and LLDB from the SDK Manager&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Start a new Android Studio project&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Android Studio and click &lt;strong&gt;Start a new Android Studio project&lt;/strong&gt;. This will initiate the new project wizard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/helloworld/step1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Start a new Android Studio project&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Select a Native C++ project&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/helloworld/step2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Select a Native C++ project&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Configure Your project&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, give your project an application name, company domain (important when deploying your app to the Play Store and also influences your Java code namespaces), project location, and package name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/helloworld/step3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Configure Your project&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Customize C++ support&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Determining what C++ Standard to use or when to upgrade can be tricky. The idea here is to use the C++ Standard thats most compatible your libraries, dependencies and existing source code. For this tutorial we’ll use the Toolchain Default. But future versions of your projects may use more modern C++…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/helloworld/step4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Configure Your project&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Project structure&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/helloworld/step5.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hello World app view&quot; style=&quot;width: 400px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Native Code in &lt;strong&gt;native-lib.cpp&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-cpp&quot;&gt;#include &amp;lt;jni.h&amp;gt;
#include &amp;lt;string&amp;gt;

extern 'C' JNIEXPORT jstring JNICALL
Java_com_rabiielbeji_helloworld_MainActivity_stringFromJNI(
        JNIEnv *env,
        jobject /* this */) {
    std::string hello = &quot;Hello Rabii from C++&quot;;
    return env-&amp;gt;NewStringUTF(hello.c_str());
 }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cmake file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cmake_minimum_required(VERSION 3.4.1)

add_library( # Sets the name of the library.
        native-lib

        # Sets the library as a shared library.
        SHARED

        # Provides a relative path to your source file(s).
        native-lib.cpp)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main java activity class &lt;strong&gt;MainActivity.java&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;// Used to load the 'native-lib' library on application startup.
static {
    System.loadLibrary(&quot;native-lib&quot;);
}

@Override
protected void onCreate(Bundle savedInstanceState) {
    super.onCreate(savedInstanceState);
    setContentView(R.layout.activity_main);

    // Example of a call to a native method
    TextView tv = findViewById(R.id.sample_text);
    tv.setText(stringFromJNI());
}

/**
 * A native method that is implemented by the 'native-lib' native library,
 * which is packaged with this application.
 */
public native String stringFromJNI();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Result after running the app&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post5/helloworld/step6.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hello World app view&quot; style=&quot;width: 400px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CODE&lt;/strong&gt;
The code is available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rabi3elbeji/NDK_HelloWorld&quot;&gt;NDK_HelloWorld&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NDK and OpenCV for object detection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;What's OpenCV?&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OpenCV (Open Source Computer Vision) is a library of programming functions mainly aimed at real-time computer vision. In simple language it is library used for Image Processing. It is mainly used to do all the operation related to Images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has a C++ interface and support Android :smile:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;OpenCV DNN module&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OpenCV DNN (Deep Neural Networks) module has been released from OpenCV 3.3 version and it’s designed for running multiple deep learning models trained from different deep learning frameworks like Caffe and TensorFlow. It supports various networks architectures based on YOLO, MobileNet-SSD, Inception-SSD, Faster-RCNN Inception,Faster-RCNN ResNet, and Mask-RCNN Inception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CODE&lt;/strong&gt;
Clone &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rabi3elbeji/NDK_OpenCV&quot;&gt;NDK OpenCV&lt;/a&gt; from github and follow usage steps&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using NDK in your applications allows them to achieve a high level of performance in terms of memory or processing time. But also, it’s not recommended to use the NDK with ordinary applications that don’t have a critical need for memory or speed performance, because Kotlin and Java are already optimized and simple to use and implement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In future posts, I will cover more examples of using Computer Vision and Deep-Learning with NDK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1- &lt;a href=&quot;https://software.intel.com/en-us/articles/android-application-development-and-optimization-on-the-intel-atom-platform&quot;&gt;Android* Application Development and Optimization on the Intel® Atom™ Platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2- &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.android.com/ndk/guides/abis&quot;&gt;Android ABIs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3- &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NT8blJ2-jeU&amp;amp;list=PLFTIxMvfPSS0WST-XWNhumx4V3-Cf47m0&amp;amp;index=2&amp;amp;t=0s&quot;&gt;Droidcon SF 2018 - Getting Started with the Android NDK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4- &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/androiddevelopers/getting-started-with-c-and-android-native-activities-2213b402ffff&quot;&gt;Getting Started with C++ and Android Native Activities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5- &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cathybgyz/zimenglyu/blob/master/_posts/2018-11-27-tflite-android-ndk-eng.markdown&quot;&gt;Android NDK eng&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6- &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/leadrien/opencv_native_androidstudio&quot;&gt;Opencv Native Androidstudio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7- &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/opencv/opencv/wiki/Deep-Learning-in-OpenCV&quot;&gt;Deep Learning in OpenCV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/blog/2018/Introduction-NDK-DeepLearning/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/blog/2018/Introduction-NDK-DeepLearning/</guid>
        
        <category>Artificial Intelligence</category>
        
        
        <category>Artificial Intelligence</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Towards Artificial Consciousness</title>
        <description>&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post4/ac.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;question-&quot;&gt;Question ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is it possible to artificially model human consciousness one day?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is almost impossible to find an exact and clear definition of consciousness. What really exists are several subjective philosophical definitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subjectivity of consciousness is due to the fact that the definition is closely related to the individualized experiences and intelligence of each human being, as well as to several other temporal and spatial factors of existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the difficulty of defining this subjective concept, let us at least agree that it exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The level of consciousness of the human being varies according to these experiences and its biological intelligence. This invisible intelligence comes from a brain made up of billions of neuronal connections and complex and fairly precise chemical reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until this highly advanced era, we are unable to understand in detail how our biological brain creates intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this complexity of the biological brain’s construction, we begin to emulate, step by step, the functioning of the human brain through mathematical models to create what is now called &lt;strong&gt;artificial intelligence&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that the consciousness of the human being is linked to his intelligence can open the door to the possibility of creating &lt;strong&gt;artificial consciousness&lt;/strong&gt; based on artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/blog/2018/Artificial-Consciousness/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/blog/2018/Artificial-Consciousness/</guid>
        
        <category>Artificial Intelligence</category>
        
        
        <category>Artificial Intelligence</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning and Deep Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post3/ai_bg.png&quot; alt=&quot;AI&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, Artificial Intelligence (AI) has had a huge impact on our daily lives like never before. Day after day, we see products that automate several tasks and serve us in an intelligent way. The proposed solutions of AI are rather personalized than standard. Today we find AI everywhere in large and small industries. Giant companies like Google, Amazon, Microsoft, Apple, Samsung, etc… spent millions of dollars in AI research to improve their products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a more professional level, when we talk about AI, we use the terms “Machine Learning” and “Deep Learning”. So, we need to define clearly what we are talking about when we mention AI .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning, and Deep Learning? How do they relate to each other?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;artficial-intelligence-ai&quot;&gt;Artficial Intelligence (AI)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the father of Artificial Intelligence, John McCarthy, it is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The science and engineering of making intelligent machines, especially intelligent computer programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence is a way of making a computer, a computer-controlled robot, or a software think intelligently, in the similar manner the intelligent humans think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The central goal of AI is to provide a set of algorithms and techniques that can be used to
solve problems that humans perform intuitively and near automatically, but are otherwise very
challenging for computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past decade, AI has given us self-driving cars, practical speech recognition, effective web search, and a vastly improved understanding of the human genome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI is so pervasive today that you probably use it dozens of times a day without knowing it. Many researchers also think it is the best way to make progress towards human-level intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the main classes of artificial intelligence is machine learning and deep learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Venn diagram describing deep learning as a subfield of machine learning which is in turn a subfield of artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post3/AMD.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;machine-learning-ml&quot;&gt;Machine Learning (ML)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a basic definition of machine learning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Algorithms that parse data, learn from that data, and then apply what they’ve learned to make informed decisions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning is the science of getting computers to act without being explicitly programmed.
Although machine learning is a field within computer science, it differs from traditional
computational approaches. In traditional computing, algorithms are sets of explicitly programmed
instructions used by computers to calculate or problem solve. Machine learning algorithms instead
allow for computers to train on data inputs and use statistical analysis in order to output
values that fall within a specific range. Because of this, machine learning facilitates computers
in building models from sample data in order to automate decision-making processes based on data
inputs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any technology user today has benefitted from machine learning. Facial recognition technology
allows social media platforms to help users tag and share photos of friends. Optical character
recognition (OCR) technology converts images of text into movable type. Recommendation engines,
powered by machine learning, suggest what movies or television shows to watch next based on user
preferences. Self-driving cars that rely on machine learning to navigate may soon be available to
consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of the most widely adopted machine learning methods are supervised learning which trains
algorithms based on example input and output data that is labeled by humans, and unsupervised
learning which provides the algorithm with no labeled data in order to allow it to find structure
within its input data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post3/machine-learning.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 600px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deep-learning-dl&quot;&gt;Deep Learning (DL)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep learning is a subfield of machine learning, which is, in turn, a subfield of artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of neural networks and deep learning is a long, somewhat confusing one. It may surprise you to know that “deep learning” has existed since the 1940s undergoing various name changes, including cybernetics, connectionism, and the most familiar, Artificial Neural Networks
(ANNs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first neural network model came from &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF02478259&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;McCulloch and Pitts&lt;/a&gt; in 1943. Then, in the 1950s the seminal Perceptron algorithm was published by &lt;a href=&quot;http://psycnet.apa.org/record/1959-09865-001&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rosenblatt&lt;/a&gt;. This model could automatically learn the weights required to classify an input (no human intervention required).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the latest incarnation of neural networks as we know it is called deep learning. What
sets deep learning apart from its previous incarnations is that we have faster, specialized hardware with more available training data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i['GoogleAnalyticsObject']=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,'script','//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js','ga');

  ga('create', 'UA-115439306-1', 'auto');
  ga('send', 'pageview');
&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/blog/2018/Introduction-AI/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/blog/2018/Introduction-AI/</guid>
        
        <category>Artificial Intelligence</category>
        
        
        <category>Artificial Intelligence</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Friendly Introduction To Steganalysis</title>
        <description>&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post2/Steganalysis_bg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 900px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous post titled “&lt;a href=&quot;../Introduction-Steganography&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friendly Introduction To Steganography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;”, we have shown that steganography, in its most common modern digital form, conceals plain text or whole files in an image, audio or video file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of communication with a very low risk of detection (for example by the naked eye for images) can be a virgin territory of misuse through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Terrorism:  According to government officials, terrorists use to hide maps and photographs of terrorist targets and giving instructions for terrorist targets. As an example, the events of September 11th prompted significant discussion and speculation as to the use of Steganography by terrorists (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Qaeda&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;al-Qaeda&lt;/a&gt;) for clandestine and secured communications.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Spying: Steganography has been a favored way to pass messages through public discussion sites and was used by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_Chapman&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Anna Chapman&lt;/a&gt; and her bumbling ring of Russian spies to pass messages online.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Hacking: The hacker hides a monitoring too, server behind any image or audio or text file and shares it with mail or chat which will get installed and executed which will help the hacker to do anything with the workstation. In a presentation at Hack In The Box in Amsterdam in 2011, &lt;a href=&quot;http://net-square.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Net Square&lt;/a&gt; security researcher &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/therealsaumil&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Saumil Shah&lt;/a&gt; demonstrated an updated method of his digital steganography project, &lt;a href=&quot;http://stegosploit.info/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stegosploit&lt;/a&gt;. Shah has discovered executable code can in fact be embedded within an image and executed in a web browser, evading detection of even the most scrupulous malware scanners.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;questions-&quot;&gt;Questions ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can we fight against the abuse of steganography? and how can we do that?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief-response&quot;&gt;Brief Response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yes&lt;/strong&gt;, like the cryptanalysis that was created against cryptography, there is also what we call the &lt;strong&gt;Steganalysis&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-whats-steganalysis-&quot;&gt;1. What’s Steganalysis ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefly, Steganalysis can be defined as the set of techniques and methods used to detect the presence of information embedded in digital objects and to extract this information if it is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-steganalysis-approaches&quot;&gt;2. Steganalysis approaches&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steganalysis algorithm may or may not depend on the steganographic algorithm (SA). Based on this, steganalysis is classified as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;21specific-or-target-steganalysis&quot;&gt;2.1.Specific or Target steganalysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SA is known and the designing of detector (steganalysis algorithm) is based on SA. The steganalysis algorithm is dependent on the SA. This type of steganalysis is based on
analyzing the statistical properties of an image that change after embedding. The advantage of using specific steganalysis is the results are very accurate. The disadvantage of using this method is it is very limited to particular embedding algorithm as well as the image format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;22blind-or-universal-steganalysis&quot;&gt;2.2.Blind or Universal steganalysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In universal steganalysis, the SA is not known by everyone. Hence, anyone can design a detector
to detect the presence of the secret message that will not depend on SA. Comparing with specific
steganalysis, universal is common and less efficient. Still universal steganalysis is widely used
than specific one because it is independent of the SA.
&lt;strong&gt;Nowadays, scientific research focuses on universal steganalysis.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post2/steganalysis_system.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-steganalysis-methods-and-tchniques&quot;&gt;3. Steganalysis Methods and tchniques&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the way of detecting the presence of hidden message, steganalysis methods are divided as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;31-statistical-steganalysis&quot;&gt;3.1. Statistical steganalysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to detect the existence of the hidden message, statistical analysis is done with the pixels. It is further classified as &lt;strong&gt;spatial domain&lt;/strong&gt; steganalysis and &lt;strong&gt;transform domain&lt;/strong&gt; steganalysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spatial domain, the pair of pixels is considered and the difference between them is
calculated. The pair may be any 2 neighboring pixels. They may be selected within a block
otherwise across the two blocks. Finally the histogram is plotted that shows the existence of the
hidden message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In transform domain, frequency counts of coefficients are calculated and then histogram analysis is performed. With the help of this, the cover and stego images can be differentiated. However, this method is not providing information about the embedding algorithms. To overcome this problem, we may choose feature based steganalysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;32-steganalysis-machine-learning-techniques&quot;&gt;3.2. Steganalysis machine learning techniques&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this method, the features of the image will be extracted for selecting and retaining relevant
information. These extracted features are used to detect hidden message in an image. They can
also be used to train classifiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes the following 2 phases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. &lt;strong&gt;Feature Extraction&lt;/strong&gt;: It is a process of creating a set of distinct statistical attributes of an image. These attributes are known as feature. Feature Extraction is nothing but a dimensionality reduction. The extracted features must be sensitive to the embedding artifacts. Image quality metrics, wavelet decompositions, moment of image statistic histograms, Markov empirical transition matrix, moment of image statistic from spatial and frequency domain, co-occurrence matrix are some of the feature extraction methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. &lt;strong&gt;Classification&lt;/strong&gt;: It is a way of categorizing the images into classes depending on their feature values. Supervised learning is one of the primary classifications in steganalysis. Supervised learning allows learning under some supervision. In this learning, a set of training inputs
that includes input features is given as input to train the classifier. After the training, class label is predicted based on the features that are given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;steganalysis use the following classifiers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multivariate regression&lt;/strong&gt;: It consists of regression co-efficient. In the training phase, regression coefficients are predicted using minimum mean square error.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FLD&lt;/strong&gt;: It is a linear combination of features which maximizes the separations. In the classification method, multi dimensional features are projected into a linear space.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SVM&lt;/strong&gt;: This classification method learns from the given sample. It is trained to recognize and assign class labels based on a given set of features.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;33-steganalysis-deep-learning-models&quot;&gt;3.3. Steganalysis deep learning models&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, Deep Learning models such as the Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN or ConvNet) have been introduced and applied within image steganalysis context. Deep learning combines the two phases in machine learning techniques(Feature extraction and classification) as a single compact model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-steganalysis-tools&quot;&gt;4. Steganalysis tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various steganalysis tools are available to detect the presence of hidden information with the stego image. Some of the steganalysis tools are mentioned below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/abeluck/stegdetect&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;StegDetect&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.petitcolas.net/watermarking/stirmark/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stirmark&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cyborg.ztrela.com/steg-toolkit.php/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;StegBreak&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aldeid.com/wiki/StegSecret&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;StegSecret&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/h3xx/jphs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;JPSeek&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cyborg.ztrela.com/steg-toolkit.php/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;StegBreak&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.petitcolas.net/watermarking/2mosaic/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2Mosaic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-good-application-of-steganalysis-in-other-fields&quot;&gt;5. Good application of steganalysis in other fields&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medical safety&lt;/strong&gt;: Current image formats such as DICOM separate image data from the text (such as patients name, date and physician), with the result that the link between image and patient
occasionally gets mangled by protocol converters. Thus embedding the patients name in the image could be a useful safety measure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intellectual property offenses&lt;/strong&gt;: Intellectual property, defined as the formulas, prototypes, copyrights and customer lists maintained by a company, can be far more valuable than the actual items they sell.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Watermarking&lt;/strong&gt;: Special inks to write hidden messages on bank notes and also the entertainment industry using digital watermarking and fingerprinting of audio and video for copyright protection.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://shodhganga.inflibnet.ac.in/bitstream/10603/8912/13/11_chapter%202.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chapter 2: Steganography and Steganalysis methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2012/05/steganography-how-al-qaeda-hid-secret-documents-in-a-porn-video/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Steganography: how al-Qaeda hid secret documents in a porn video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.player.one/hacking-pictures-new-stegosploit-tool-hides-malware-inside-internet-images-instant-444768&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hacking With Pictures; New Stegosploit Tool Hides Malware Inside Internet Images For Instant Drive-by Pwning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i['GoogleAnalyticsObject']=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,'script','//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js','ga');

  ga('create', 'UA-115439306-1', 'auto');
  ga('send', 'pageview');
&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2018 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/blog/2018/Introduction-Steganalysis/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/blog/2018/Introduction-Steganalysis/</guid>
        
        <category>steganalysis</category>
        
        
        <category>steganalysis</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Friendly Introduction To Steganography</title>
        <description>&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post1/steganography_bg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drawing&quot; style=&quot;width: 900px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;question-&quot;&gt;Question ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a software developer or computer science, networks student or simply a web surfer, you may hear the word cryptography. The aim of using cryptography is to provide a secure communication while transmitting data throw network supports. Cryptography techniques modify the data to make them incomprehensible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here I have a simple question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can we transmit secret data without applying cryptography techniques throw network supports and trusted their security at the same time?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief-response&quot;&gt;Brief Response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yes&lt;/strong&gt;, the response is &lt;strong&gt;Steganography&lt;/strong&gt;. Nowadays, steganography is defined as the art and science of hiding or embedding secret data through various multimedia containers or network supports such as videos, audio files, network packets and last but not least digital images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-a-bit-of-history&quot;&gt;1. A bit of history&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steganography is an old practice that has been around for a long time. People have desired to keep certain sensitive communications secret for thousands of years. The term steganography combines the Greek words &lt;strong&gt;steganos&lt;/strong&gt;, meaning “covered, concealed, or protected” and graphein meaning “writing”.
The first recorded uses of steganography can be traced back to 440 BC when ancient Greece, people  wrote messages on wood and covered it with wax that bore an innocent covering message. In 1499, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_Trithemius&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Johannes Trithemius&lt;/a&gt;, introduce officially the concept of steganography in his book titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steganographia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Steganographia&lt;/a&gt;. In the last centuries, Steganography used during both world wars essentially in the espionage using secret inks in letters or photos. Recently, we have seen new generation of steganography called digital steganography used in many malware programs and cyber espionage tools. Four main trends of development of the so-called digital steganography can be distinguished:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;digital media steganography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;linguistic steganography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;file system steganography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;network steganography&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summary of the evolution of the steganographic data carrier is presented in the figure down below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post1/steganography_timeline.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; title=&quot;Steganographic evolution&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-whats-a-stegosystem-&quot;&gt;2. What’s a Stegosystem ?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Stegosystem&lt;/strong&gt; describes the process that is used in performing steganographic methods. Let’s say that &lt;strong&gt;Alice&lt;/strong&gt;, the expeditor, want to send a secret message to &lt;strong&gt;Bob&lt;/strong&gt;, the receiver, using a stegosystem. Alice uses a steganographic method to embed the secret message (&lt;code&gt;M&lt;/code&gt;) through a cover object (&lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt;). The embedding process generates a stego object (&lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;). Alice sends the stego object to Bob clearly through the network without any encryption using a web or mobile application for example. In the other side, Bob must use the same steganographic method to extract the secret message (&lt;code&gt;M&lt;/code&gt;) from the received stego object (&lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;). Note that some steganographic methods use a stego key (&lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;) in the embedding process to provide more security to the secret message. In this case, Bob must have the same stego key (&lt;code&gt;K&lt;/code&gt;) used by Alice to extract the secret message (&lt;code&gt;M&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post1/stego_system.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; title=&quot;A standard Stegosystem&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main keywords used in the most stegosystems are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cover Object&lt;/strong&gt;:  The cover object is the carrier of the hidden message.  A cover is generally chosen in a manner that it appears most ordinary and innocuous and does not arouse suspicion as such. The cover object can be :
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Text file (txt, pdf, word, …)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Image file (jpeg, png, gif, ppm, …)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Audio file (wav, mp3, aac, …)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Video file (mp4, avi, mov, flv, …)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Network protocol (tcp/ip, pop, smtp, http, …)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stego Object&lt;/strong&gt;: The cover object with a secret message concealed within it is known as the stego.
It is used on the recipient side for extracting the hidden message.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stego Key&lt;/strong&gt;: Stego  key  is  a  key  to  embed  data  in  a cover and extract data from the stego medium.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embedding Domain&lt;/strong&gt;: refers to the cover medium characteristics that are exploited in embedding message into it. It may be spatial domain when direct modification of the constituent elements of the cover is modified (e.g. pixels in an image) or it can be the frequency domain or transform domain if mathematical transformations are carried on the medium before embedding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-steganographic-methods&quot;&gt;3. Steganographic methods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steganographic methods can be classified mainly into five categories, although in some cases this classification is not possible:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spatial domain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transform domain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spread spectrum&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Statistical Methods&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Distortion Methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;31-spatial-domain&quot;&gt;3.1. Spatial domain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spatial domain steganographic techniques, also known as substitution techniques, are a group of
relatively simple techniques that create a covert channel in the parts of the cover image in which
changes are likely to be a bit scant when compared to the human’s eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the ways to do so is to hide information in the Least Significant Bit (LSB) of the image data.
This embedding method is basically based on the fact that the least significant bits in an image can
be thought of as random noise, and consequently they become not responsive to any changes on the image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;32-transform-domain&quot;&gt;3.2. Transform domain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transform domain embedding can be defined as a domain of embedding techniques for which a number of algorithms have been suggested. The process of embedding data in the &lt;em&gt;frequency domain&lt;/em&gt; of a
signal is much stronger than embedding principles that operate in the &lt;em&gt;time domain&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transform domain techniques have an advantage over LSB techniques because they hide information in areas of the image that are less exposed to compression, cropping, and image processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;33-spread-spectrum-technique&quot;&gt;3.3. Spread Spectrum Technique&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spread spectrum transmission in radio communications transmits messages below the noise level for any given frequency. When employed with steganography, spread spectrum either deals with the cover image as noise or tries to add pseudo-noise to the cover image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;34-statistical-method&quot;&gt;3.4. Statistical Method&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also  known  as  model-based  techniques,  these  techniques  tend  to  modulate  or  modify  the
statistical properties of an image in addition to preserving them in the embedding process. This
modification is typically small, and it is thereby able to take advantage of the human weakness in
detecting luminance variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;35-distortion-techniques&quot;&gt;3.5. Distortion Techniques&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Distortion techniques require knowledge of the original cover image during the decoding process where
the decoder functions to check for differences between the original cover image and the
distorted cover image in order to restore the secret message. The encoder, on the other hand, adds a  sequence of changes to the cover image. So, information is described as being stored by signal distortion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-characteristics-of-a-strong-steganography-method&quot;&gt;4. Characteristics of a Strong Steganography method&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though steganography’s most obvious goal is to hide data, there are several other related goals used to judge a method’s steganographic strength. These include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capacity&lt;/strong&gt; (how much data can be hidden)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invisibility&lt;/strong&gt; (inability for humans to detect a distortion in the stego-object)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Undetectability&lt;/strong&gt; (inability for a computer to use statistics or other computational methods to differentiate between covers and stego-objects)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robustness&lt;/strong&gt; (message’s ability to persist despite compression or other common modifications)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tamper resistance&lt;/strong&gt; (message’s ability to persist despite active measures to destroy it)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Signal to noise ratio (SNR)&lt;/strong&gt; (how much data is encoded versus how much unrelated data is encoded).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three main components, which work in opposition to one another, are &lt;em&gt;capacity&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;undetectability&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;robustness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-perfermance-measure&quot;&gt;5. Perfermance measure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a performance measure for image distortion due to embedding, the well-known peak-signal-to-noise ratio (&lt;code&gt;PSNR&lt;/code&gt;), which is categorized under difference distortion metrics, can be applied to stego images.  It is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post1/psnr_function.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous equation, &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is the maximum fluctuation in the input image data type. For example, if the input image has a double-precision floating-point data type, then &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is 1. If it has an 8-bit unsigned integer data type, &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; is 255, etc. &lt;code&gt;MSE&lt;/code&gt; denotes the mean square error, which is given as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post1/mse_function.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;M&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;N&lt;/code&gt; are the number of rows and columns in the input image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;MSE&lt;/code&gt; represents the cumulative squared error between the stego and the cover image, whereas PSNR represents a measure of the peak error. The lower the value of &lt;code&gt;MSE&lt;/code&gt;, the lower the error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Structural Similarity (&lt;code&gt;SSIM&lt;/code&gt;) Index quality assessment index is based on the computation of three terms, namely the luminance term, the contrast term and the structural term. The overall index is a multiplicative combination of the three terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post1/ssim_function.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-scientific-and-commercial-applications&quot;&gt;6. Scientific and commercial applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, there are many applications for Information Hiding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advanced data structures&lt;/strong&gt;: We can devise data structures to conceal unplanned information without breaking compatibility with old software. For instance, if we need extra information about photos, we can put it in the photos themselves. The information will travel with the photos, but it will not disturb old software that does not know of its existence. Furthermore, we can devise advanced data structures that enable us to use small pieces of our hard disks to secretly conceal important information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medical imagery&lt;/strong&gt;: Hospitals and clinical doctors can put together patient’s exams, imagery, and their information. When a doctor analyzes a radiological exam, the patient’s information is embedded in the image, reducing the possibility of wrong diagnosis and/or fraud. Medical-image steganography requires extreme care when embedding additional data within the medical images: the additional information must not affectthe image quality.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strong watermarks&lt;/strong&gt;: Creators of digital content are always devising techniques to describe the restrictions they place on their content. These technique can be as simple as the message “Copyright year by Someone”, as complex as the digital rights management system (&lt;code&gt;DRM&lt;/code&gt;) devised by &lt;code&gt;Apple Inc.&lt;/code&gt;  in its &lt;code&gt;iTunes&lt;/code&gt; store’s contents, or the watermarks in the contents of the Vatican Library.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Military agencies&lt;/strong&gt;:  Militaries’ actions can be based on hidden and protected communications.   Even with crypto-graphed content,  the detection of a signal in a modern battlefield can lead to the rapid identification and attack ofthe involved parties in thecommunication. For this reason, military-grade equipmentuses modulation and spreadspectrum techniques in its communications.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intelligence agencies&lt;/strong&gt;: Justice and Intelligence agencies are interested in studying these technologies, and identifying their weaknesses to be able to detect and track hidden messages.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Document tracking tools&lt;/strong&gt;:  We can use hidden information to identify the legitimate owner of a document. If the document is leaked, or distributed to unauthorized parties, we can track it back to the rightful owner and perhaps discover which party has brokenthe license distribution agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Document authentication&lt;/strong&gt;: Hidden information bundled into a document can contain a digital signature that certifies its authenticity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General communication&lt;/strong&gt;: People are interested in these techniques to provide more security in their daily communications. Many governments continue to see the internet, corporations, and electronic conversationsas an opportunity for surveil-lance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital elections and electronic money&lt;/strong&gt;: Digital elections and electronic money are based on secret and anonymous communications techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radar systems&lt;/strong&gt;: Modern transit radar systems can integrate information collected in a radar base station, avoiding the need to send separate text and pictures to the receiver’s base stations.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remote sensing&lt;/strong&gt;: Remote sensing can put together vector maps and digital imagery of a site, further improving the analysis of cultivated areas, including urban and naturalsites, among others.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-scientific-research&quot;&gt;7. Scientific research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steganography is an active theme in scientific research that follows the development of technology. Nowadays, several laboratories and scientific researchers around the world are doing intense work that leads to a significant evolution of digital steganography during this century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend this list for those who want to do scientific research in steganography&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laboratories&lt;/strong&gt;:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dde.binghamton.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DDE - Digital Data Embedding Laboratory, SUNY Binghamton, Binghamton, NY, USA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lirmm.fr/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LIRMM - Laboratoire d’Informatique de Robotique et de Microélectronique de Montpellier, France&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ece.uic.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ECE - Department, University of Illinois at ChicagoChicago, IL, USA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scientific Researchers&lt;/strong&gt;:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ws.binghamton.edu/fridrich/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dr. Jessica Fridrich&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dde.binghamton.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DDE Lab members &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lirmm.fr/~chaumont/Resume.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dr. Marc Chaumont&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source codes&lt;/strong&gt;:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dde.binghamton.edu/download/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DDE Lab download website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Datasets&lt;/strong&gt;:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dde.binghamton.edu/download/ImageDB/BOSSbase_1.01.zip&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BOSSbase_1.01 from DDE Lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lirmm.fr/~chaumont/SteganalysisWithDeepLearning/CroppedBossBase-1.0-256x256_cover.rar&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cropped BOSSBase from LIRMM Lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dde.binghamton.edu/download/ImageDB/BURST_sorted.zip&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BURST_sorted from DDE Lab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;8-an-overview-to-the-next-post&quot;&gt;8. An overview to the next post&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steganography has undergone a significant evolution during the last two centuries through various
techniques and methods that serve to increase the undetectability of the stego object. The misuse of
steganography by hackers and terrorists requires the existence of an antidote. This antidote is steganalysis which aims to detect the existence of a stego object in a first step and to extract the secret message in a second step. A Brief introduction to steganalysis in the “&lt;a href=&quot;../Introduction-Steganalysis&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;next post&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steganography&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steganography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hindawi.com/journals/scn/2017/5397082/#B22&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.hindawi.com/journals/scn/2017/5397082/#B22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://securelist.com/steganography-in-contemporary-cyberattacks/79276/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://securelist.com/steganography-in-contemporary-cyberattacks/79276/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cse.wustl.edu/~jain/cse571-09/ftp/stegano/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.cse.wustl.edu/~jain/cse571-09/ftp/stegano/index.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ijarcs.info/index.php/Ijarcs/article/viewFile/2483/2471&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.ijarcs.info/index.php/Ijarcs/article/viewFile/2483/2471&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Osamah_Al-qershi/publication/292310394_Image_Steganography_Techniques_An_Overview/links/57f642ac08ae8da3ce574080/Image-Steganography-Techniques-An-Overview.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Image Steganography Techniques: An Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mathworks.com/help/vision/ref/psnr.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.mathworks.com/help/vision/ref/psnr.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mathworks.com/help/images/ref/ssim.html?s_tid=doc_ta&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.mathworks.com/help/images/ref/ssim.html?s_tid=doc_ta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Structural_similarity&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Structural_similarity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/ftp/arxiv/papers/1202/1202.5289.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Development Trends in Steganography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/f60e/d5f0f609956d0715659c823506feea036a31.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Steganography and Steganalysis in Digital Multimedia: Hype or Hallelujah?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/share&quot; class=&quot;twitter-share-button&quot; data-show-count=&quot;false&quot;&gt;Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  (function(i,s,o,g,r,a,m){i['GoogleAnalyticsObject']=r;i[r]=i[r]||function(){
  (i[r].q=i[r].q||[]).push(arguments)},i[r].l=1*new Date();a=s.createElement(o),
  m=s.getElementsByTagName(o)[0];a.async=1;a.src=g;m.parentNode.insertBefore(a,m)
  })(window,document,'script','//www.google-analytics.com/analytics.js','ga');

  ga('create', 'UA-115439306-1', 'auto');
  ga('send', 'pageview');
&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/blog/2018/Introduction-Steganography/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rabi3elbeji.github.io/blog/2018/Introduction-Steganography/</guid>
        
        <category>steganography</category>
        
        
        <category>steganography</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
